Guide to the Spanish Advertising Broadsides (Auca and Alelujas), 1938-1985 and undated RL.11006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Spanish, 1938-1985 and undated; 1
  - 34. Bomba Prat water pumps. Aleluya de la "Bomba Prat" o una solución verdad--Aleluya of "Bomba Prat"; or, a true solution, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A farmer is struggle to get his crops to grow because of the sever lack of water present that season. He prays and does everything he can to try to make his crops successful but they continue to fail nonetheless. One day we comes across "Bomba Prat" a pump that is supposed to draw water from the ground and make it readily available. After purchasing this pump, his crops begin to grow and his harvest is so succesful that be becomes rich.
  - 35. Casa Piulachs. Es probado y es notorio la eficacia del papel para hacer un envoltorio--The efficacy of this paper to serve as wrapping paper is tried and renowned, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Many shop owners are notorious for using cheap wrapping paper that comes undone easily, which leaves their clients very unhappy. Instead of using newspaper or this cheap wrapping paper, CASA PIULACHS offers a much better alternative. They print store's information on high quality wrapping paper that can be used to advertise the business and keep the customer happy. This alternative helps the business owner save money on advertisements and attracts more customers because of the high quality wrapping paper that is used.
  - 36. Industrias Reunidas de Utensilios Metalicos (IRUM). Es un termo lo mejor para el frío y el calor--It's the best thermos for cold and hot, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: This thermos can be used in a vast array of situations and environments. Mothers, fathers, bikers, skiiers, pilots, the eldery, the sick and many more people can use it to keep their soups or drink either hot or cold. Even Satan can use this thermos to keep his water cold in hell. Anyone who resists using it will surely regret it.
  - 37. Caldo OXO en cubitos. El Caldo OXO en Cubitos de la compañia LIEBIG--OXO brand bouillon cubes from the Liebig Company., Undated (Box 1)
    Trademark of OXO was designated in 1899. Dehydrated bouillon cube. Commercialised by OXO in 1910. OXO was sold by UNILEVER to the Campbell soup company in 2001. Summary of text: Although a homemade meal is great, it can very easily take four hours to prepare. When one is short on time Caldo OXO en cubitos is the perfect solution. This soup is delicious and ready in only minutes. It's perfect for an elderly man who that lives by himself or soldiers who are out in battle and do not have access to other meals.
  - 38. Para qué y para quien sirven los libros--For who and for what do books serve, 1956 (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Books are the most useful resource as many people can benefit from them and because they serve a variety of purposes. They can be read for fun, to learn about medicine, to read law, to know more abut history or to win over a true love. Everyone is encouraged to buy books.
  - 39. Book fair. Auca de la vida y aventuras de un libro viejo--Auca of the life and adventures of an old book, 1956 (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A 100 year old book tells his life story which begins in a book store. He is purchased by a young couple and for many years the book gets passed from owner to owner. Eventually he falls in love with another book and they travel to Paris. Unfortunately he finds himself left alone in Paris and spends the rest of his years bitter about deteriorating, old age until one day a man restores him to a prior conditions. Now he will be at the upcoming book fair waiting for an owner to permanently add him to his collection.
  - 40. Frigo Yogurt. Aleluyas del Yogur Frigo--Aleluyas of Frigo Yogurt, Undated (Box 1)
    Frigo is part of the Unilever company in Spain and was founded in 1948. Summary of text: Yogurt is a snack that is enjoyed on all (5) continents by many, many people. Scientists have proven that it has lots of health benefits and FRIGO makes the experience even more enjoyable by making delicious, natural yogurts with fresh fruit.
  - 41. Fonobilingue. El saber no ocupa lugar o El que aprende puede llegar--Knowing doesn't require a place; or He who learns can arrive (at his goal), Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A young man is looking to learn French and begins using records created by FONOBILINGUE to learn the language. He quickly picks up on it and as a result is able to receive many more opportunties because of his language ability. He eventually also learns English. Because of his vast language abilities and the help of FONOBILINGUE he is now very successful.
  - 42. Auca Confortcamp, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Confortcamp is a cot-like device that is meant to me a light and easy to carry item. It can be used in various situations such as camping or for going to the beach and it also has other accessories that can be purchased to extend the already wide usability of this item.
  - 43. National lottery. Auca de la Lotería o la historia de unas tías que les toco la lotería--Auca of the lottery or The history of some aunts who won the lottery, 1952 (Box 1)
    Summary of text: One of three sisters seem to be sad and struggling when one day she wins the lottery. Because of this she is able to travel, buy nice things and meet a nice man who she eventually marries and has twin girls with. They live a happy life and the 2 daughters grow up to want to win the lottery as the ad claims that the lottery makes everything possible.
  - 44. La rata sus costumbres. Precausiones que debe adoptar contra la misma--Rats. Their customs. Precautions you should take against them, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: This is more of a public service announcement as to how to prevent rats from entering their house than it is an ad. It gives advice such as keeping windows closed, keeping lids on trash cans, not leaving and food on the counters and know where to put your rat posion. However, it does not advertise or ever mention a particular poison or product to be used for this purpose.
  - 45. Wynn's automotive products. Vida más larga y segura, para su motor, Señor--A longer and more secure life for your engine, Sir, Undated (Box 1)
    USA brand of car care products founded in 1939. Summary of text: To test out the capabilities of an engine, two men are put to a test involving a vehicule and two eggs. The men are supposed to drive and as soon as they hit 80km the passenger should drop the egg out of of his window. Then some WYNN's is put into the engine and the same procedure is repeated. The second time, the egg is dropped farther because the Wynn's product helped revive the engine and make the vehicule run faster.
  - 46. POTAX. Aleluya que te enseña, la tradición navideña--Aleluya that shows you the Christmas tradition, 1941 (Box 1)
    Maker of food products, now owned by Unilever. Summary of text: Christmas season is a great holiday to spent with family. The children are eating sweets and everyone is excited about the festivities and food. However, cooking requires a lot of time and patience so instead families should you POTAX soup which will be filling and will satisfy.
  - 47. Baños populares. Anales de la dulce y Hermosa Elvira--Tales of the sweet and beautiful Elvira, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Elvira is trying to take a bath at home but encounters many difficulties in attempting to do this. Because she does not have a bathtub, she must heat up water and fill up a small basin that she will bathe in. This ends up being very messy and water is spilt all over the kitchen floor. Elvira then has to spend a lot of time cleaning up and this process leaves her dirty again. When her husband comes home she is very agitated so he suggests going to the public bathrooms where bathtubs are also available. Elvira is able to take a wonderful bath and leaves BAnOS POPULARES feeling clean and looking beautiful. She is the talk of the town and her husband's lust towards her is renewed.
  - 48. Baños populares. Baños populares de Barcelona--Public bathrooms in Barcelona, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: This auca tell the same story as auca #47 but in a different format. The drawings are on one side of the sheet while the story is broken up into pieces on the other side. The reader is supposed to number each part of the story to correspond to the correct drawing.
  - 49. National Lottery. Gran idea ese a fe mia - esta de la lotería--Grand idea, this of the lottery, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: This auca's purpose seems to serve as a means to build hype about the lottery drawing. It tells the stories of many people that would like to win and all the things that could be done with the money won.
  - 50. Auca del GIB (firm), Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: GIB is a company that produces entertainment for children. As they are usually bored when they have to attend events that are typically more entertaining for adults, such as religious holidays and birthdays for adults, GIB has provided a cure for the children's boredom. They put on events that include trapeze events, ventriloquists, plays and theatre, magic shows and so on.
  - 51. Teatro Barcelona - Gracia y Justicia--Barcelona Theatre - Humor and Justice, 1940 (Box 2)
    Gracia y Justicia: Spanish Film from 1940, directed by Julian Torremocha and starring Mary Santamaria and Mario Gabarron. Summary of text: Humor and Justice is a play that will follow Trinidad, a local gypsy, who falls in love and gets married. Trinidad and her husband have a child and all seems to be going well until another woman falls in love with Trinidad's husband. What will Trinidad do? What will become of her marriage? All the audience can know is that by the end, Trinidad will go from being a gypsy to being a classy woman.
  - 52. Salon de proyecciones = Rambla del centro, 34--Movie House, Center Rambla, 34 (location), Undated (Box 2)
    Movie theater that dates back to the early 1900s. Summary of text: A young boy is given a real (currency) and decides to go to the SALON DE PROYECCIONES to watch movies and enjoy all day entertainment. When the boy does not show up at home later on in the day, his parents become very worried and phone the police. In searching for the boy they decide that he was probably gone off to a movie theatre. When the boy is found, his mother is very angry but the police man says she has no reason to be since the boy was smart enough to spend his money on something worthwhile. The family agrees and decides to watch movies until dinner time.
  - 53. Public service announcement. Aleluyas para contribuir a evitar accidentes de la circulación: Dedicadas a los niños de las escuelas primarias--Aleluyas to avoid car accidents: dedicaded to elementary school aged children, 1943 (Box 2)
    Summary of text: This aleluya is basically a list of tips for young children who will be crossing the street. It includes tips such as looking both ways when crossing the street and knowing what different colored stop lights mean.
  - 54. Grafia Hispana magazine. Solo nos faltaba "ver" el auca de Gutenberg--We just had to "see" Gutenberg's Auca, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Before the printing press, there were many other forms of recording written material that other societies were utilizing such as scrolls and eucalyptus but those were never very time efficient and did little for mass printing. After Gutenberg invented the printing press, the printing industry changed. GRAFIA HISPANA is a magazine that keeps its readers up to date about new methods and techniques for printing.
  - 55. Brillol. Maravillas de BRILLOL--BRILLOL's wonders, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: BRILLOL is a metal-cleaning product that comes in either liquid or paste. It does such a fantastic job at cleaning metal that it's been used by angels to brighten the stars and even the sun has been blinded by seeing its reflection in a BRILLOL cleaned product.
  - 56. Auca de la Maxima Garantia del comprador--Auca of the maximum garauntee for the buyer, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: This ad includes descriptions of the services that multiple businesses provide. A map is included. Many of the characters portrayed appear to be Mexican (based on their attire). Many of the men are wearing sombreros or charro outfits (typically worn my men who are in a mariachi band). There are also French translations for the entire Auca.
  - 57. Artesanías Forcano. En esta "Auca" se relata la historia de la alpargata--The story of the alpargata is told in this "auca", Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Alpargatas are flat and comfortable shoes that have been used for many different situations throughout history. These shoes make it much easier for people to go who are planning on taking a long, strenuous walk or for women whose heels are becoming incresingly bothersome. ARTESANIAS FORCANO provides alpargatas in many different styles and heel heights. They are often used by locals and tourists alike.
  - 58. Blendi toothpaste, Undated (Box 2)
    Blendi is a product acquired by Procter amd Gamble in 1987 that is advertised under Blend-A-Med. In most other countries, this brand name is Crest but is advertised under the name of Blend-A-Mend in many countries in EuropeSummary of text: Blendi is an otter who has very white teeth and who has decided to help a young boy who does not like brushing his teeth. Blendi shows the young boy that this toothpaste, also named BLENDI, tastes good and also effectively fights cavities.
  - 59. Esposition. Aleluyas del Vino--Aleluyas of Wine, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: This aleluya contains some history of wine but besides that it focuses on the benfits of wine and all the countries that can attest to this. There will be lots of wine at the Exposition Fair which is something that no one should miss.
  - 60. La Bruxa Borracha (restaurant)--The Drunk Witch, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: A woman who was long ago accused of being a druken witch receives pardon and begins cooking. She ends up cooking for a restaurant (La Bruxa Borracha) which becomes the new "chic" restaurant in town.
  - 61. Argentina Bar Restaurante. Auca de "Arca de Noe" para el papá y el bebe--Auca of "Noah's Ark" for the father and child, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Noah's ark arrives full of animals who end up celebrating their survival so intensely that many of them get hurt and have to visit the veterinerian. In order to cover the cost, the ark opens up as a sort of zoo for people to come to visit to see the animals.
  - 62. Molfort's. Historia del Calcetín--The story of the sock, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Socks have been used by many, many successful conquerer's and warriors throughout the years and are part of the reason as to why they have been so successful. For example, when Christopher Columbus introduced himself to those native to America, they were completely fascinated by his use of socks. MOLFORT'S is a business that provides socks. Everyone knows that they are the solution.
  - 63. IBERIA (shaving products). El mas Importante invento - es el que cuento--The most important invention is the one that I am talking about, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Shaving has been an issue for many men - and sometimes even women and children until IBERIA razor blades came along. With these new blades, shaving can be much more effective and pain free.
  - 64. El Cantabrico. Aleluya original que de "El Cantabrico" cuenta, en versos, que no estan mal, la cocina suculenta--Original aleluya about "El Cantabrito", the succulent kitchen, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Restaurant El Cantabrico serves some of the freshest, best tasting food in town. Their food is always fresh and they get new ingredients every day. If you ever do visit this restaurant, you'll be visiting everyday simply based on how good it is.
  - 65. Fiesta Mayor. Auca de la fiesta mayor, Undated (Box 2)
    Summary of text: Similar to aunca #56 Auca de la Maxima Garantia del comprador, this auca is an ad for various businesses that will be at the Fiesta Mayor that is coming up. There are ads for liquor, clothing, furniture, meat markets and more.
  - 66. Ramblas de Barcelona. Auca de la Ramblas, 1953 (Box 2)
    Summary of text: The Rambla of Barcelona is a street located in the city with many shopping opportunities. There are business that offer a variety of products as well as numerous hotels. This area is visted by local and tourists alike.
  - 67. Philips. Lamparas de garantía?--Warrantied lamps?, 1985 (Box 2)
    Summary of text: A man who is constantly buying cheap light bulbs keeps getting into accidents when the bulbs suddenly go out. As a result of trying to save money on the light bulb, he has medical bills that arise from the accidents he has gotten into. If he had simply spent a little more on PHILIPS light bulbs, he would have never had any issues.
- Catalan, 1946-1979 and undated; 2
  - 68. Mataro Fair. Adam I Eva a la Fira de Mataro--Adam and Eve at the Mataro fair, Undated (Box 2)
    Mataro is the capital of Maresme.
  - 69. Ciutat Comptal. La guia comercial - D'un troc de ciutat comptal--Commercial guide for Ciutat Comptal [?], Undated (Box 2)
    Ciutat Comptal is a reference to Barcelona's business district [?]
  - 70. Us oferim I'auca origina del clot comercial--We offer the story of the origins of the commercial district [?], Undated (Box 2)
  - 71. Auca del paper CARLETS--Story of Carlets papers (for cigarettes), Undated (Box 2)
    Carlets is a brand of cigarette rolling paper.
  - 72. Us oferim l'auca original del comerc I mataro industrial--We offer the story of the origins of Mataro's trade and industry [?], Undated (Box 2)
  - 73. Auca de Barcelona--Story of Barcelona, 1950 (Box 2)
  - 74. Auca de Sant Gervasi--Story of Sant Gervasi, Undated (Box 2)
    Sant Gervasi is a district in Northwestern Barcelona
  - 75. Auca historia I rodona del futbol club barcelona--History of the Barcelona soccer club [?], Undated (Box 2)
  - 76. L'auca del primer ferrocarrilaqui trobarau combinada amb l'historia d'en biada--Story of the first railroad [?], Undated (Box 2)
  - 77. Auca de bella-terra--Story of Bellaterra [?], Undated (Box 2)
    Bellaterra is a suburb in Barcelona
  - 78. Gracia Festival. Auca de la festa major de gracia comercos acreditats:--Story of the authorized shops for the Gracia festival [?], Undated (Box 2)
    Gracia Festival takes place currently in August in the Gracia neighborhood of Barcelona
  - 79. Auca dels magatzems Alemanys--Tale of Alemanys, Undated (Box 2)
    Magatzems Alemanys was an early department store in Barcelona
  - 80. Teatro Romea La compania maragall de Carlos Lloret y Luis Nonell con la eximia Maria Vila--Teatro Romea, the company of Carlos Lloret and Luis Nonell with the superb Maria Vila, Undated (Box 2)
    Teatro Romea was built in Barcelona in 1863 as a Catalan language theater. Carles Lloret (1921-2006) and Lluis Nonell (1926-1982) were notable Catalonian actors.
  - 81. Auca dels magatzems Alemanys--Tale of Alemanys, Undated (Box 2)
  - 82. Auca dels aplecs de la sardana (II)--Tale of the Sardana gathering, Undated (Box 2)
    Sardana is a circle folk dance of Catalonia
  - 83. Auca dels aplecs de la sardana--Tale of the Sardana gathering, Undated (Box 2)
  - 84. La ferreria--The blacksmith, 1967 (Box 2)
  - 85. Auca del bon bibliofil--Tale of the bibliophile, Undated (Box 2)
  - 86. Auca de la tisis (Aventuras del microbi de la tuberculosis)--The thesis (story of the tuberculosis microbe), Undated (Box 2)
  - 87. Llibret Auca de la Pastisseria Publicat per Forn de Sant Jaume S.A Barcelona--Story of the Bakery published by the Oven of Saint James SA, Barcelona, Undated (Box 2)
    Forn de Sant Jaume is a bake shop and cafe in Barcelona, still in operation
  - 88. Auca del perfecte futbolista--Tale of the perfect football player, Undated (Box 2)
  - 89. Auca de "Les Set Portes"--Tale of the Seven Doors, 1961 (Box 1)
    Les 7 Portes is a restaurant in Barcelona
  - 90. Puig. Auca de Puig cerda Meitat d'Espana, meitat de Franca, no hi ha terra, com la Cerdanya--Tale of Puig, halfway in Spain and in France, there is no place like Cerdanya [?], Undated (Box 1)
    Puig is a fashion and fragrance business. Cerdanya is in the Pyrenees.
  - 91. Guardiet. Auca de Mobles Guardiet- Historia d'un casament--Tale of Guardiet Furniture: story of a wedding, Undated (Box 1)
    Guardiet is a home furnishings and appliance store
  - 92. Auca d'En Filigrana, campio de Futbol--Tale of "En Filigrana," soccer champion, circa 1937 (Box 1)
  - 93. Festival, Falla Joaquin Costa--Conde de Altea. A modo de introduccio precisa esta explicacio. Auca del llibret dela falla dels carrers de joaquin costa I conde altea, del an 1946--A way of precise introduction is explained. Tale of the booklet of the celebration in the streets of Joaquin Costa in the Conde of Altea. (Box 1)
    Falla Joaquin Costa--Conde de Altea, a festival, takes place in March.
  - 94. Calendari del Llaminer, 1979 (Box 1)
    Seems to be highlighting different holidays celebrating in this part of Spain
  - 95. L'auca de radio scope (versificada per la colla de Taradell)--Tale of the radio scope (verse from Taradell) [?], Undated (Box 1)
    Taradell is a town near Barcelona
  - 96. Auca dels 'Torrons puig d'agramunt'--Tale of the Torrons of Mount Agramunt [?], 1956 (Box 1)
    Turrones, a nougat-type of confection from the locality of Agramunt in Catalonia
  - 97. Per poguer be repartir, un "Patria" haureu de tenir--for distribution, there is a fatherland [?], Undated (Box 1)